good evening everyone it's 630 and I now call to order this February 11th 2025 meeting of Lancaster City Council a few things at the top of the meeting first an announcement we had an executive session it was held this evening Tuesday February 20 25th February 11th 2025 excuse me this evening at 6 p.m. at Council Chambers City Hall to discuss personnel and legal matters related to a pension disability request of michael deets thank you president oh that's later sorry i'm gonna that's gonna that will appear in our legislative agenda this evening i'm gonna continue with my other reminders at the top of the meeting uh this meeting and its participants are being recorded please take a moment to silence your phones and other devices as a courtesy to others if you haven't done so already during this meeting there will be several opportunities for public comment anyone making comment should do so at the microphone right in front of you there so you can be heard comments should be related to issues that have or may come before council as legislative items and should be addressed toward council rather than to others in the room each speaker will be given three minutes to keep time you will see the light here in front of me turn green when a speaker begins it'll turn yellow when there's one minute remaining and it will turn green when three minutes has been exhausted thank you to everyone in advance for ensuring that everyone has equal time and now for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the pledge
of Allegiance mr. Harris would you please call the roll of members yes
madam president mr. met here mr. royal here mr. Cleese yeah miss Greg here miss Diaz here mr. Hirsch here president Baker here we'll now move to the
approval of the minutes of the January 28th 2025 regular meeting of counsel motion to approve second we have a motion and a second are there any
council comments on the minutes hearing none mr. Harris mr. man I mr. Roya I mr. Glees I miss Craig all right miss Diaz I mr. Hirsch all right
the president Baker I the next item on our agenda our proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition which we have won this evening resolution number 9 2025 mr. Harris this minute president resolution of the
council the city of Lancaster designating February 2025 as Black History Month in the city of Lancaster and recognizing resistance to injustice by injustice by African Americans throughout Lancaster history motion to
approve second we have a motion and a second
councillor Craig council president this resolution was read into record during the committee meeting last week and I don't feel the need to reread it because
it's quite lengthy Thank You councillor Craig and thank you for reading that into our meeting record and we thank you and the work that you did together as with previous years this was drafted with the help of the local chapter of the NAACP are there any additional comments council comments on the
resolution the council president if I may counselor I'm ed I just want to thank councillor Craig for introducing this resolution and I want to thank the city of Lancaster for its commitment to celebrating black history month especially in a time nationally where it does not seem to be prioritized so I just want to thank members of council and thank the city for its commitment to our black community here in Lancaster Thank You councillor I'm an additional
comments from members of council from the public on the resolution very none
mr. Harris mr. Mudd hi mr. Roy oh hi mr. Cleese hi mr. Craig hi miss Diaz hi mr. Hirsch hi the president Baker hi thank you the
next item on our agenda is public comment this is section reserved for residents of contacted the city clerk prior to the meeting to request the opportunity to address City Council again duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker just confirming mr. Harris are there any public comments for this period no matter president when no one contacted me in advance of the me thank you very much then we'll rule we'll move on to our next agenda item this evening which is reports requested by counsel I don't believe we have any of those is that correct mr. Harris that is correct thank you the next item on our agenda is reports of committees of council these are the meetings held on February 3rd 2025 we begin with the Public Safety Committee councillor Diaz the public safety did not meet Thank You councillor Diaz Public Works Committee councillor Hirsch Thank You council president the
Public Works Committee had three agenda items all of which will be seen in our in our agenda this evening here at Council resolution 10 authorizing cost-sharing agreement man I'm Township and resolutions 15 and 16 which are seeking approval for use of right-of-way their permit applications and agreements that are to be made with railway auditing management services and Norfolk Southern and that concludes the report of the Public Works Committee Thank You
councillor harsh Economic Development Committee councillor med Thank You
council president the Economic Development Committee did not meet thank
you Finance Committee counselor Arroyo Thank You council president the Finance Committee did meet we had three items on our agenda for that evening we discussed resolution number 1225 amending the supplemental pension plan for city employees and resolution number 1325 exonerating of utility fees excuse me exoneration of utility fees both of those items will be on the agenda later this evening we also received an update on a bond issuance from director Campbell she gave an overview of an upcoming general obligation bond issuance that will be brought forward to council in a proposed ordinance the bond issue will be for a total of fifty three point excuse me fifty five point three million dollars and the debt will be divided among the general fund water fund and sewer fund next month we will also have a list a list of the projects that will be funded by the bond issue that concludes my
report council president Thank You councillor Arroyo community planning
committee councillor Craig Thank You council president community planning did meet we had one item on the agenda that was administration resolution 1425 adopting substantial amendments to community to community development block grant annual action plan and that will come up on our agenda our legislative
agenda and just a little book thank you very much councillor Craig and personnel
committee councillor colleagues thank you madam president the personal Committee did meet on February 3rd and review a nomination to reappointment to the city revitalization and improvement zone authority that conclude my reports
thank you very much we'll now move into our legislative agenda the first item is an authorization of action this is related to our executive session and this would be authorizing or denying a request for disability pension for Michael Dietz I believe council Craig you wanted to address this thank you
upon recommendation of the Bureau of police officers relief the police pension board City Council met in an exact executive session to review the disability pension application of Michael Dietz based upon the unanimous recommendation of the police of the Bureau of police officers relief and the information provided to counselors during the executive session I hereby make a move to approve Michael Dietz application for a disability pension
second Thank You counselor Craig we have a motion and a second to approve the request are there any council comments on the motion from the public hearing
none mr. Harris mr. met I mr. Roy oh hi mr. Cleese I miss Craig I miss Diaz mr.
Hirsch all right the person Baker I move into the second item on our legislative agenda this evening these are nominations for appointments councillor
clicks thank you madam president that this nomination was this was with you to February 3rd by the personal committee and full consoles now I'll make a motion to reappoint the Shelby Norman to the city revitalization and improvement zone authority for a term from December 31st of 2024 to December 31st of 2029
second we have a motion and a second on the appointment any additional council comments from the appointment of miss Nauman from the public hearing none mr.
Harris mr. Mennon aye mr. Roya aye mr. Cleese aye mr. Craig aye
miss Diaz aye mr. Hirsch aye president Baker aye next item is item C resolutions we begin with administration resolution number 10 2025 mr. Harris a resolution
of the council the city of Lancaster approving an inter-municipal agreement for cost sharing of Marshall Avenue roadway base repairs between Mannheim township and the city of lancaster motion to approve second we have a motion and a second
this is coming through public works councillor hirsch thank you council president um this
resolution is essentially uh entering the city into a cost-sharing agreement with maynham township as many of you may know marshall avenue is along the northern border and southern of the city and the southern border of man i'm township um and it zigzags pretty chaotically and so this kind of allows the city to enter into an agreement where um they are taking on the portion of the cost that uh is proportionate to the city's ownership of the road which in this case these improvements are primarily going to be to improve uh biking and walking infrastructure along marshall ave total cost is roughly 62 000 so it's a pretty low cost project on the whole the city is going to take 82 percent of that as they own 82 percent of that roadway it's not a full resurfacing project it's base improvements to the roadway to allow the additional infrastructure to be put in and my understanding is that the work is slated to take place later this year it's a correct director Campbell is nodding so that's pretty much the deal
with with this room thank you very much council Hirsch I'll just say whoever figured out that we owned 82% specifically of the road at kudos to them spent a lot of time in GIS I bet yeah any additional council comments on
the resolution from the public hearing none mr. Harris mr. Redd aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Cleese aye mr. Craig aye miss Diaz mr. Hirsch aye the next item is
administration resolution number 11 2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the council
of the city of Lancaster approving the pride flag raising to acknowledge the start of Pride Month in June 2025 as brought forth by the Lancaster pride
Association motion to approve second we have a motion and a second members of council thank you so much for allowing me to introduce this resolution this is for a flag raising that will take place on June 2nd 2025 with the inclement weather date of June 3rd 2025 the the request was submitted in a timely manner and we look forward to raising the flag again this coming June for Pride Month there any additional council comments on the resolution from the public hearing
none mr. Harris mr. Matt hi mr. Roy hi mr. Glees hi miss Craig Craig all right
miss Diaz hi mr. Hirsch hi and president Baker hi our next item on the agenda is resolution number 12 2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the city of the city of
lancaster lancaster county pennsylvania amending the city of lancaster supplemental pension plan in order to reflect that the effective january 1st 2023 i'm sorry that effective january 1st 2023 the matching percentage with respect to a police officer hired on or before on or after january 1 2011 became equal to 35 percent of the amount contributed by the participant
motion to approve second we have a motion and a second on the resolution this is coming through the finance committee counselor arroyo thank you council president director campbell uh went
through this resolution during our last finance committee meeting we are amending the city of lancaster supplemental pension plan to reflect the correct amount of matching contribution for police officers hired on or after january 1 of 2011. the plan currently incorrectly states that this is a 25 this is 25 so this resolution will correct the matching contribution amount to 35 we reinstated the plan last year at this time in february of 2024 with the inclusion then of firefighters who were included starting in january 2024 however we didn't make the correct uh excuse me however we failed to make the correct to the matching percentage for police at that time this resolution will correct that thank you very much counsel Arroyo are there
any additional counsel comments on the resolution from the public hearing none
mr. Harris mr. Mudd aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Cleese aye miss Greg all right miss
Diaz mr. Hirsch aye president BK aye we will now move to administration resolution number 13 2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the of the council the
city of Lancaster exonerating 2024 water charges in the amount of sixty three thousand seven hundred dollars and fifty cents and sewer charges in the amount of sixty four thousand one hundred and ten dollars and sixty four cents for city owned or related properties at 25 locations motion to approve second we
have a motion and a second councillor Arroyo Thank You council president this
is a resolution that is brought before council on an annual basis it is done because the city tracks water and sewers sewer usage as city properties mostly to detect leaks or unusual usage we don't bill ourselves for this usage the charges are exonerated annually to clear them from the financial accounts two properties on the list are not city owned the library and the fire line at the Lancaster Airport the water and the sewer service to the library is considered an in-kind contribution from the city and the service to the airport is done in exchange for the airport providing the city use of its large capacity snow blowers in case of a storm thank you very much council royal are
there any additional council comments on the resolution from the public hearing
done mr. Harris mr. men ah mr. Roy oh hi mr. Glees hi miss Greg all right
miss Diaz mr. Hirsch hi hi we will now move to resolution number 14 2025 mr.
Harris a resolution of the council the city of Lancaster authorizing the mayor to submit substantial amendments for the following documents one the combined 2021 to 2025 consolidated plan and the 2021 annual action plan and to the 2022 annual action plan and three the 2023 annual action plan and for the 2024 annual action plan to the US Department of Housing and Urban Development the submission includes projected changes in the use of funds for the Community development block grant program during the 2021 2022 2023 and 2024 programs motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second counselor craig thank you council president as presented by deputy director geyser and community development administrator jen rummel at committee meeting on the third they are recommending substantial amendments to each of the annual action plans from for 2021 through 2024. the proposed amendments to the program would increase funding for the critical repair program and lead hazard reduction program administrations administrations by administrations by 199 000 community facilities by 75 000 and affordable housing solutions approximately three hundred and five three hundred five thousand two hundred also in the presentation listed are the four areas that would see reduction primarily due to spending caps within the CDBG program that that was presented by deputy director geyser and Jen Rommel and if there's any questions i see that um miss geyser is here thank you very much counselor craig
miss geyser do you have anything to add yes thank you thanks for the summary uh the lengthy summary of our long amendments um this evening i just wanted to uh highlight two things um that we are recommending these changes presuming that we will get the 2025 cdbg funding for the city however with the uncertainty in the federal government the federal allocations for CDBG may change and if our allocation significantly changes we would have to reassess our substantial amendments and potentially come back to you with additional changes which we try not to do but that may be required if there is an unexpected decrease next year I also wanted to note that last week we received a question about our total efforts toward affordable housing since we are reallocating on about 300,000 to affordable housing and I wanted to provide just a snapshot of the total dollars the city has invested in affordable housing because it's just astronomical and noteworthy so since 2018 we have allocated eight point one million dollars for 492 lead hazard control projects 1.5 million dollars for 152 home repair projects 4.4 million dollars for 363 units of affordable housing that was rehabilitated and 11.6 million dollars for 284 new affordable housing units and the grand total is 25.6 million dollars invested in affordable housing um representing a commitment by you the city council and the mayor to this initiative and although we are only able to reallocate 300 000 across five years the total allocation is more than a million dollars over the five years just from cdbg alone and we've been able to accomplish this unprecedented funding by allocated allocating small amounts large amounts big grants small grants throughout all these years um to accumulate to this total so i wanted to just bring that to your attention and thank you all again for your commitment to affordable housing
over all the years thank you very much rebecca and thank you for that summary i think that's important to keep that in perspective little projects and big projects yes Yes. Additional comments from council on the resolution from the public. Good evening.
Good evening. Susie Gomez, 100 Block of North Reservoir Street. Thank you. Can you explain to me CBBG funding? Is that government funding? Yes, that's federal government funding. OK. So total investment of, you said, $25.6 million?
The $25.6 million that I was referencing just now was the amount of affordable housing investment we've made since 2018 to 2024 across many different funding streams. The CDBG allocation is about $1.5 million per year.
And that is government funding, correct? Yes. OK. The other question would be, you had mentioned increased funding. The $305,000 is being allocated, is that correct? Reallocated. Reallocated. So you're going from 2020 to 2024 to show rejected funds? Can you explain that a little better?
Ms. Gomez, just to make sure you keep your time, is there anything further that you'd like Ms. Geyser to explain?
She can explain it now. Okay. That's why I'm asking. Great. Just wanna make sure.
Yeah. Ms. Geyser? So due to changes over the past four years in spending, mostly due to caps and staff vacancies, we have needed to change how we anticipated to spend the money to what is realistic at this point today. And so these changes represent reallocating money that we had previously allocated or council had previously allocated from 2021 to 2024 and shifting them from one bucket of into other buckets and primarily critical repair and lead hazard control and affordable housing Thank You mr. yes so one last question
um you want to reassess and make changes for what for what you're reassessing
these funds from the years we are required to update these plans as funds are reallocated into these different categories so we are doing that with
this measure yeah but you're turning it in you're you're also really doing the annual action plan right you're taking all that into consideration without so meaning that there is funds available for housing and that's what these fun
and and we are reallocating unspent funds from staffing vacancies over the past four years into affordable housing and lead hazard control and critical repair projects so they're getting more money the affordable housing and critical repair projects are receiving more funding out of administrative
costs and into the actual affordable housing yes so my point very quickly was
just that because of that there's funding available we have a housing crisis in Lancaster City and I think that is very unfair to the public any
additional public comments on the resolution hearing on and before we go I'll just make clear to council as this guys are reiterated twice during her presentation that these are funds that are being reallocated into affordable housing support of the products and out of administrative costs mr. Harris the next item on our legislative agenda is administration resolution number 15 2025
mr. Harris a resolution of the council of the city of Lancaster authorizing the mayor to sign the standard height lease I'm sorry height license agreement between Norfolk Southern Railway Company and remit a payment of $5,000 for fees required to the license agreement on behalf of the city of Lancaster motion to
approve second we have a motion and a second council hirsch thank you council president uh
resolutions number 15 and 16 are very similar in nature they are essentially agreements that give us or we are essentially approving the ability to use the right of way to do future infrastructure projects in this case it's a ductile pipe that is in columbia pennsylvania as part of our water infrastructure there and so applying and paying this permit fee essentially allows uh that work to be done um that's really all there is to this thank you very much counselor
are there any additional comments on the resolution from council from the public hearing none mr. Harris next item on the agenda is administration resolution number 16
2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster authorizing the mayor to sign a standard-type license agreement between between Railway Auditing and Management Services and a permit of $6,750 for fees required in the license agreement on behalf of the City of Lancashire.
Motion to approve. Second.
We have a motion and a second. Councilor Hirsch, this sounds similar.
Yes, pretty much the same thing. It's just entering into an agreement with Railway Auditing and Management Services in this case as opposed to Norfolk Southern, which is previous resolution. um yeah just paying the permit fee to allow right of uh use to um replace or to conduct work there
so thank you very much any additional council comments on resolution 16. from the public hearing none, Mr. Harris
Mr. Minton, aye Mr. Sorolla, aye Mr. Lease, aye Mr. Gregg, aye Ms. Stevens, aye Mr. Grish, aye and President Baker, aye
that concludes our legislative agenda if I'm following along correctly and we'll take this to our second public comment period this evening, this is open for comment on issues not previously on the agenda duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker and please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record if anyone wishes to make a public comment please come up to the podium at this time hearing none we'll close the second public comment period this evening and we will move to our next item which is the report of
the mayor mayor sir thank you council president first i'm pleased to share that the city of lancaster along with the school district of lancaster was awarded 74 000 by the pennsylvania commission on crime and delinquency the state grant will allow a school district and partners to research and design an effective cross-sector intervention strategy to reduce gun and group-related violence in Lancaster, and I'm truly grateful for our partnership with the district. Additionally, applications for police officers and cadets positions are now open. We are eager to bring on new officers and cadets. The cadet program, as you know, bridges the gap between high school graduation and turning Turn 21, for those who are interested in pursuing a career in law enforcement. The application is just open on February 1st, and we have 77 officer applications so far and 260 people who have expressed interest. Encourage all of you to help us get the word out, so thank you in advance. And check out lcbpcareers.com for more information. And second, I want to spotlight the Department of Neighborhood Engagement. It's become a tradition that on Valentine's Day, which is coming up on Friday, and I know everybody's just thinking about the Eagles Parade, but do not forget your Valentine's. The department announces new initiatives and launches applications for their long-standing programs. The state-old Love Your Block grants are back, now entering its seventh year. The program awards grants to residents dedicated to revitalizing their neighborhoods through community-led projects. Love Your Block is made possible through the generous support of the Hyde Foundation. we're also launching the neighborhood art project which is designed to encourage public art and create a place making in our neighborhoods so the call for artists will also go out on february 14th inviting local artists to apply for opportunities to create public art that reflects the vibrancy and diversity of lancaster community the neighborhood art project is supported by the national endowment for the arts and you can learn more about these programs and apply to take part at the city of lancaster.gov forward slash neighborhoods and that concludes my report tonight thank you council president thank you mayor sirachi uh the next item on the agenda
is a report president of council i do not have a report to make this evening uh so we'll move to our next item which is council comments are there any council comments this evening
i just wanted to report back to the members of council that the government study transition committee did meet on january 29th and went over the purview of our work which is to make sure and ensure the transition to a homework charter moves in a timely manner with both the administrative code and the ethics commission our next meeting will be tuesday april 29th at 5 p.m in council chambers it will also be live streamed and i just wanted to report back that we did meet and the purview of our work is to ensure the timely transition to the newly elected home rule charter that concludes my report
thank you councilman and i appreciate you taking the time to serve on that important board any additional council comments hearing on and reaching the end of our agenda this evening
i'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn all in favor aye we're adjourned thank you